JOE: Dietary habits can be difficult
to understand and sometimes, to manage.
They may involve different issues
such as eating only a few foods, only
eating at home, going long periods
without food or eating ‘nonfoods’
a condition known as ‘pica’.
Many autistic people suffer with
obsessions, and if certain foods or
calorie counting, is their obsession,
this could lead to over-eating,
under-eating or a rigid diet.
BETH: If an individual has problems
with overeating, reducing their
food portions, using a smaller plate
may help, or limiting the amount of
food readily available in the house.
It’s a good idea to have a set timetable
for meal-times and setting limits around
visiting restaurants and take-aways.
If an individual has under eating
problems, increasing food portions
or using a bigger plate may help,
as will increasing their contact
with foods of different varieties.
JOE: Visual aids can also be used for
both problems showing foods that are
good and foods that are not so good,
and also showing visual representations
of hunger and fullness scales.
BETH: Some individuals with
autism experience pica, which
is eating or mouthing non-edible
items, such as stones and dirt.
The reason a person on the autism spectrum
might experience pica, could be medical,
dietary, sensory or behavioural . They
may do this for a range of reasons
such as not understanding which items
are edible, liking the texture of
the item, to relieve pain or anxiety
or as a method of gaining attention.
JOE: An obsession with eating, could
be channelled into something positive
such as cooking and writing recipes.
Special interests could be used
to encourage them to eat more
volume or variety, by cutting the
food into shapes or by looking at
foods from different countries.
BETH: Many autistic people
rely on routine and sameness.
They may need to have meals at the
same time every day, sit in the same
position at the table, or always use
a certain plate or bowl and cutlery.
They may also like processed foods as
they are predictable, and look and taste
the same each time, whereas fresh food
or homemade food may vary in taste.
JOE: It’s important to remember though,
that like all people, sometimes, obsessive
eating can be a coping strategy and
over-eating or avoiding food may be a
result of low self-esteem or anxiety.